<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy</title>
    <link>https://b-hemanth.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://b-hemanth.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Chowkidar Campaign: What is the Twitter Sentiment?</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/2019/03/21/chowkidar-campaign-what-is-the-twitter-sentiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/2019/03/21/chowkidar-campaign-what-is-the-twitter-sentiment/</guid>
      <description>Analysis of Twitter Reactions to the BJP’s #Chowkidar Campaign I analyzed a mixed sample of the most popular and most recent one hundred and eight thousand tweets in English from the last three days (as of 20 March, 2019, 10:07 pm EST) on the Bharatiya Janata Party’s #MainBhiChowkidar campaign.
# # Tibble and text processing # temp_1 &amp;lt;- x %&amp;gt;% # # Lose useless columns # select(created_at, text, favourites_count, retweet_count) %&amp;gt;% # # Convert text to lower text # mutate(text = tolower(text)) # # Note: https://hackernoon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Hello!
I am Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy, an undergraduate student at Harvard interested in development and behavioral economics. I concentrate in Applied Math &amp;amp; Economics with a secondary in Computer Science. I spend my free time telling stories with data, reading about education policy, and arguing feminist theory. I talk a lot about politics and my beautiful hometown of Chennai, India.
I work as a research assistant at the Harvard Kennedy School for Professors Michela Carlana, David Deming, and Mahzarin Banaji, and Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/about/</guid>
      <description>About    About GitHub LinkedIn    1 min read About 2019-03-18 Hello! I am Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy, a first-year undergraduate student at Harvard University. I aspire to a career in research and academia. I plan to pursue a Concentration in Applied Mathematics and Economics with a Secondary in Computer Science. I am deeply interested in economics, data science, public policy, computer science, and feminist theory. I am also a parliamentary debater (I debated for Team India in school, and now do so for the Harvard College Debating Union).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>