<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy</title>
    <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://b-hemanth.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gunshots in DC - Web App</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/04/22/gunshots-in-dc-web-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/04/22/gunshots-in-dc-web-app/</guid>
      <description>I built a web app with Ilkin Bayramli studying gunshots in Washington D.C. We do interactive geospatial animated analysis of gunshot data: i.e., select your inputs to view animated maps of gunshots in DC in different time periods.
Shiny App link!
GitHub for code and ReadMe.
Thanks to Jillian Carr and Jennifer Doleac for building the shotspotter dataset with the Justice Tech Lab in DC. The way the shotspotter dataset is made is quite interesting: &amp;ldquo;acoustic sensors detect the sound of gunfire and record the precise timestamp as well as the triangulated location of all gunfire incidents in a covered area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter in the Biggest Election - Web App</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/03/27/follow-up-on-the-chowkidar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/03/27/follow-up-on-the-chowkidar/</guid>
      <description>Studying Twitter&amp;rsquo;s response to the Main Bhi Chowkidar (I too am a guard) electoral campaign of the Bharatiya Janata Party (Background, Wiki), analyzing it using machine learning to study sentiments, representing views geospatially on a map, studying tweet frequency lumping and potential bot activity, and more!
Shiny App Link!
Github for code and ReadMe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to GitHub and R Markdown (Guest Lecture at Stella Maris College, Chennai)</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/03/22/introduction-to-github-and-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/03/22/introduction-to-github-and-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>Notes from a guest lecture I delivered in March 2019 at the Department of Computer Science at Stella Maris College, Chennai, offering a simple introduction to GitHub with R and R Markdown.
1 GitHub 1.1 What is GitHub?  Cloud-based version control system But what is version control?
 - Simple analogy: Google Drive for developers - Track and manage changes to your code - Version control lets developers safely work through branching and merging - Work with online Git repository - Make changes in your own branch - Merge with online cloud branch - Changes are tracked and can be reverted if needed   1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chowkidar Campaign: What is the Twitter Sentiment?</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/03/21/chowkidar-campaign-what-is-the-twitter-sentiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/blog/2019/03/21/chowkidar-campaign-what-is-the-twitter-sentiment/</guid>
      <description>Analysis of Twitter Reactions to the BJP’s #Chowkidar Campaign I analyzed a mixed sample of the most popular and most recent one hundred and eight thousand tweets in English from the last three days (as of 20 March, 2019, 10:07 pm EST) on the Bharatiya Janata Party’s #MainBhiChowkidar campaign.
# # Tibble and text processing # temp_1 &amp;lt;- x %&amp;gt;% # # Lose useless columns # select(created_at, text, favourites_count, retweet_count) %&amp;gt;% # # Convert text to lower text # mutate(text = tolower(text)) # # Note: https://hackernoon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>