<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy</title>
    <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Hemanth Bharatha Chakravarthy {year}. [Written](https://github.com/b-hemanth/my_page) in [Blogdown](https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown).</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="https://b-hemanth.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[Work-Post] RBI Report on Trends and Progress in Banking in India 2019-20</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/rbi-rtp-contribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/rbi-rtp-contribution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m privileged to share that I&amp;rsquo;ve contributed to the 2019-20 RBI Report on Trends and Progress in Banking in India. Do check out Chapter 2 (and Box II.1 therein), co-authored with Dr. Snehal Herwadkar, Director of Banking Research and the incredible editor of the report, and (the amazing) Bhanu Pratap on global savings since COVID-19: &lt;a href=&#34;https://rbidocs.rbi.org.in/rdocs/Publications/PDFs/4GLOBALBANKINGDEVELOPMENTS55F68B71F7A342F78129D0839EB4F9EE.PDF&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or better, read the entire report &lt;a href=&#34;https://rbidocs.rbi.org.in/rdocs/Publications/PDFs/0RTP2020_F3D078985540A4179B62B7734C7B445C9.PDF&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dalal Street vs. North Block</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/dalal-street-vs-north-block/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/dalal-street-vs-north-block/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-gap&#34;&gt;The Gap&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday (on the 15th of October), as many predicted, the market crashed with the SENSEX falling by over 1,000 points, all sectoral indices were in the red, and equity investors &lt;a href=&#34;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/sensex-drops-220-points-on-weak-global-cues-nifty-tests-11900/articleshow/78674278.cms&#34;&gt;lost&lt;/a&gt; Rs 3.3 lakh crore (INR 3300 billion). With severe unemployment, destroyed demand, poor fiscal stimulus announcement after announcement, loan restructuring, and the previous aggressively long position of the market, both a general decline and this particular crash seem warranted. However, today, on the 16th, the SENSEX is up by around 250 points, seemingly recovering 25% of the wealth lost yesterday. This volatile bounce back triggered me to write on the growing, increasingly volatile gap between global stock markets and real economy and attempt to describe the difference between Dalal Street and Delhi&amp;rsquo;s North Block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main intention of this post is to share this graph (the two lines have a correlation of 0.506 and the two rates have a &lt;em&gt;t-value&lt;/em&gt; of 5.45 with a &lt;em&gt;p-value&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lt; 0.001):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://b-hemanth.com/post/2020-10-16-dalal-street-vs-north-block.en_files/dalal_st.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;some-thoughts&#34;&gt;Some Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not think we understand this gap or its wideness perfectly yet, both at home and globally. But a few perspectives seem sensible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I think there is a market perception of a definite recovery. For one, there is the idea that given that everything has already crashed, things can only move upwards. Further, it seems to me, there is an expectation (almost an implicit reliance) on the idea that fiscal stimulus and government intervention will and must happen (it has happened globally, to some extent). This seems to be keeping market appetites up as, if things will only go up hereon, long positions seem more warranted. There is some value to this line of throught: Deutsche Bank &lt;a href=&#34;https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/markets/stocks/news/dichotomy-between-markets-and-economy-can-you-still-benefit/articleshow/76505316.cms?utm_source=contentofinterest&amp;amp;utm_medium=text&amp;amp;utm_campaign=cppst&#34;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; total fiscal and monetary stimulus at more than US$ 10 trillion in the G7 countries alone which will make it five times more than the stimulus the G7 rolled out after the 2008 Global Financial Crisis. While central banks have tried to ensure that the market doesn&amp;rsquo;t crash to a severe extent, it seems like their actions carry disproportionate weight in market enthusiasm. So much so that the RBI had to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.b-hemanth.com/post/who-should-borrow/&#34;&gt;intervene&lt;/a&gt; to rationalize yields on state bonds recently. As the Economist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/leaders/2020/05/07/the-market-v-the-real-economy&#34;&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; this month, &amp;ldquo;This rosy view from Wall Street should make you uneasy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But second, as many experts point out, it seems like the markets are growing increasingly detached from real world outcomes, betting purely on future profits. Business fundamentals seem to remain poor and lost demand is yet to revive, but the market doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to care. As JP Morgan &lt;a href=&#34;https://privatebank.jpmorgan.com/gl/en/insights/investing/why-stocks-rally-while-the-real-economy-suffers#:~:text=The%20gap%20between%20the%20real,flows%20for%20businesses%20and%20households.&#34;&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;The S&amp;amp;P 500 is only 15% below its all-time high, reached on February 19, 2020, and it trades with a forward price-to-earnings multiple that is the highest since the dot-com bubble in 2000.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Economist does a good job of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/leaders/2020/05/07/the-market-v-the-real-economy&#34;&gt;pointing out&lt;/a&gt; why this is all dangerous, pointing to the devastation a second crash could now cause if/when nations enter second waves of infections and if cost-cutting doesn&amp;rsquo;t save the GDP after all, incentivizing fraud as hiding your losses is more important when the market is recovering aggressively (whose eventual revelation would also shock the economy), and the anti-corporate political backlash that could ensue if big corporations continue to grow while smaller ones struggle. All of this mean that the &amp;ldquo;things can only get better&amp;rdquo; narrative is dangerous and might itself cause crashes in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who Should Borrow? The Fiscal Federalism Debate</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/who-should-borrow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/who-should-borrow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-rbi-is-buying-states-debt-for-the-first-time-ever&#34;&gt;The RBI is buying states&amp;rsquo; debt for the first time ever&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The RBI &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloombergquint.com/business/in-a-first-rbi-to-buy-state-government-bonds#:~:text=In%20A%20First%2C%20RBI%20To%20Buy%20State%20Government%20Bonds&amp;amp;text=In%20a%20first%20of%20its,interest%20costs%20amid%20high%20borrowings&#34;&gt;just announced&lt;/a&gt; (three hours ago today, the 9th of October) that it is conducting open market operations on state government bonds. That is, the RBI is going to be buying loans of states. This is the first time in history that this move is being made.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A bond is an instrument of debt. When you buy it, you give the government money which will be returned to the owner of the instrument at a later date with interest. That is, you buy debt.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;fiscal-federalism-catch-up-with-this-debate&#34;&gt;Fiscal federalism: catch up with this debate&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This move is very interesting especially in the context of the debate on who should borrow (particularly to make up GST shortfalls). So far, states say that the center should borrow and give to the states because it gets a better interest rate. Meanwhile, the center says its deficit is too high (or that it wants to preserve the room for deficits to increase) and, so, states should do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, in the non-COVID recent past, there has been an effort to create differentiated rates for different states. The rationale for this being: why should, say, Maharashtra or Tamil Nadu pay the same rate on debt as Uttar Pradesh despite distinctly better fiscal performance. Any reading of this debate immediately brings parallels to the European Central Bank and how Greece/the PIIGS nations launched into a sovereign debt crisis (i.e., couldn&amp;rsquo;t pay back their debt) due to severe fiscal indiscipline (spending too much to win elections) because they were enjoying the low rates enabled by the implicit debt guarantee on their borrowings (given contagion&amp;mdash;aka crisis spreading&amp;mdash;risk for the Euro area) from the European Central Bank and, therefore, France-Germany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;this-debate-under-covid-19&#34;&gt;This debate under COVID-19&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in the post-COVID era, especially with the GST shortfall, the question is should we prioritize a very federalist fairness, set efficient market rates, and reward and enable good governance or should we (indirectly) subsidize debt for poorer states?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all perhaps why RBI Governor Shaktikanta Das &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloombergquint.com/business/in-a-first-rbi-to-buy-state-government-bonds&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; today, &amp;ldquo;This is important from the point of view of smooth and seamless transmission of monetary policy impulses as well as &lt;strong&gt;the completion of market borrowing programmes of the centre and states in a non-disruptive manner&lt;/strong&gt; with a normal evolution of the yield curve.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;states-need-funds&#34;&gt;States need funds&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As is, even discounting the public health costs and the need for much larger expenditure to revive our economy after the virus, states&amp;rsquo; capital expenditure&amp;mdash;spending on infrastructure or projects&amp;mdash;has been steadily declining due to lower funds. With restrictions on borrowing, states have been spending mostly on revenue expenditure&amp;mdash;i.e., mostly paying salaries for existing work. This likely means there’s a significantly lower than desirable multiplier on state expenditure. In other words, every rupee spent by the government is someone&amp;rsquo;s income, who then spends it to create someone else&amp;rsquo;s income, and so on &lt;em&gt;ad infinitum&lt;/em&gt;. So, when an external party, i.e., the state adds new consumption, it has a &amp;ldquo;multiplier&amp;rdquo; effect on everyone. Typically, when you spend on infrastructure, you create a far better multiplier effect besides the direct economic benefits of having new roads or, say, more electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-does-this-all-work&#34;&gt;How does this all work?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, for the first time ever, RBI is buying the debt of states. This will be bought in the secondary market at a market-linked price&amp;mdash;where existing owners of bonds sell them to buyers. So, as states issue more bonds, more people will buy them because the RBI is buying them from you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A usual auction of bonds has a &amp;ldquo;spread.&amp;rdquo; The spread is the additional money that the investor seeks on top of the bond&amp;rsquo;s value to buy it&amp;mdash;it is how the market sets the prices of bonds. So, right now, with states increasing borrowings after COVID-19, spreads are naturally higher&amp;mdash;the more indebted you are, your additional new debt becomes less attractive. &lt;strong&gt;So, if spreads remain high, either fewer people invest in state governments or they do so with a less attractive deal for states.&lt;/strong&gt; The RBI doing this will reduce the spreads on bonds by making them a more investable asset. So, this will allow states do more auctions and get more funds. As per the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rbi.org.in/Scripts/BS_PressReleaseDisplay.aspx?prid=50439&#34;&gt;RBI calendar&lt;/a&gt;, states are expected to borrow an additional Rs 2 lakh crore during the October to December quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will also rationalize and cool down the yields on SDLs (as state bonds are called&amp;mdash;state development loans) which have been a bit crazy in comparison to central government bonds (G-Secs or government securities). &amp;ldquo;SDLs are going through the roof at about 100 basis points (bps) right now, and hopefully that will come down,&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cnbctv18.com/economy/open-market-ops-in-state-debt-papers-should-cool-yields-axis-bank-7153321.htm&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; Neeraj Gambhir, the CEO of Axis Bank, to CNBC-TV18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-will-this-be-implemented-many-interesting-questions&#34;&gt;How will this be implemented? Many interesting questions.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much of which bonds/states at what prices will the RBI end up buying? What will be the effect of this on the pricing of state government bonds? How lower will spreads get now that the RBI is showing confidence in state debt and demanding it more?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inspecting Indian Education Inspectors: Six Changes to Make</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/inspecting-education-inspectors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/inspecting-education-inspectors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;under-maintenance-sorry&#34;&gt;Under Maintenance, Sorry!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;check-out-a-latest-post-herehttpswwwb-hemanthcompostwho-should-borrow&#34;&gt;Check out a latest post &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.b-hemanth.com/post/who-should-borrow/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indian Migrants During COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/covid19-indian-migrants/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/covid19-indian-migrants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A report I led for Cefala, Schofield, and Kaur at the Behavioral Development Lab, Chennai, studying the household economy, food security, access to state services, location, health and health information, and beliefs of migrant workers during COVID-19: &lt;a href=&#34;https://behavioraldevlab.org/policy_insights/ld_covid/ld_covid_report1.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downloadable data and documentation: &lt;a href=&#34;https://behavioraldevlab.org/resources/data_ld_covid1.html?resourceId=4&amp;amp;status=all&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to GitHub and R Markdown (Guest Lecture at Stella Maris College, Chennai)</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/introduction-to-github-and-r-markdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/introduction-to-github-and-r-markdown/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Notes from a guest lecture I delivered in March 2019 at the Department of Computer Science at Stella Maris College, Chennai, offering a simple introduction to GitHub with R and R Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;github&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1 GitHub&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-github&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.1 What is GitHub?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud-based version control system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;But what is version control?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  - Simple analogy: Google Drive for developers
  - Track and manage changes to your code
  - Version control lets developers safely work through branching and merging
  - Work with online Git repository
  - Make changes in your own branch
  - Merge with online cloud branch
  - Changes are tracked and can be reverted if needed&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-github&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2 Why GitHub?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t really have a choice—industry standard!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud backup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaboration, version control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t have to reinvent the wheel: use existing Git repos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community review of your code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other uses: GitHub forum, hosting websites, GitHub Classroom, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;setup-for-rstudio&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.3 Setup for RStudio&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make your account and install into RStudio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sign up at www.github.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In console: &lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;
- If this doesn’t work, you might need to update your R
- Update at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.r-project.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start your first project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new GitHub Repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(If collaborative) Open options in your repo -&amp;gt; Share with collaborators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the GitHub repo: Clone or Download -&amp;gt; Copy the repo link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In RStudio: File -&amp;gt; New Project -&amp;gt; Version Control -&amp;gt; Git -&amp;gt; Paste the link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check out Git tab in top right corner alongside Environment, History, and Connections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quick note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gitignore: what local files or filetypes should Git ignore in prompting you to Commit in the Git tab? (e.g., &lt;code&gt;*.Rproj&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readme: let people know what cool thing you’re building in your &lt;code&gt;readme.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.datacamp.com/community/tutorials/git-setup&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.datacamp.com/community/tutorials/git-setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;three-main-git-functions&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4 Three Main Git Functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commit: create a new commit containing the current contents of the index and the given log message describing the changes (&lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-commit&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-commit&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push: push the local version of directory into your Git directory, i.e, your repo (&lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-push&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-push&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull: pull the current online version of the project into your local directory. Used when the online version has been edited since you last clones/pulled. Maintains both the changes in the online version and your local version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very simple guide on the workflow: &lt;a href=&#34;http://rogerdudler.github.io/git-guide/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://rogerdudler.github.io/git-guide/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more detailed guide: &lt;a href=&#34;https://happygitwithr.com/rstudio-git-github.html&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://happygitwithr.com/rstudio-git-github.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;working-with-git-from-the-shell&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.5 Working with Git from the Shell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;man git&lt;/code&gt; in Shell for help&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commit: &lt;code&gt;git commit -m &amp;quot;Commit message&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push: &lt;code&gt;git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull: &lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;more-resources&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.6 More Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub Cheat Sheet: &lt;a href=&#34;https://education.github.com/git-cheat-sheet-education.pdf&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://education.github.com/git-cheat-sheet-education.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A solid introduction: &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004668&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004668&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r-markdown-aka-rmd&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2 R Markdown (aka Rmd)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-rmd&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.1 What is Rmd?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“R Markdown is a file format for making dynamic documents with R. An R Markdown document is written in markdown (an easy-to-write plain text format) and contains chunks of embedded R code, like the document below.” - &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/articles_intro.html&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/articles_intro.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-rmd&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2 Why Rmd?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is written in Rmd! So cool!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Rscripts is cumbersome: Rmd lets you analyze and present data in one go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can publish as html, pdf, and word doc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatically LaTeXs if you publish to pdf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can handle complex scientific and mathematic notation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;setup&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3 Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very simple. Next time you make a new file, make it a R Markdown file instead of a R script and save it as &lt;code&gt;x.Rmd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;chunks-and-chunk-options&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4 Chunks and Chunk Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chunks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mini-R-script in the middle of your text, headings, etc. in Markdown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.g.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
# Making a random dummy dataframe
x &amp;lt;- data.frame(replicate(5,sample(0:1,1000,rep=TRUE)))
# Print three rows of our dummy df
x[1:3,]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   X1 X2 X3 X4 X5
## 1  0  1  1  0  0
## 2  0  1  1  1  1
## 3  1  0  0  0  0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chunk Options&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not want to show your code, the warnings, and messages but show the output–Rmd let’s you control that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.g.: There’s a hidden chunk below but you’ll only see the table it outputs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;html {
  font-family: -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &#39;Segoe UI&#39;, Roboto, Oxygen, Ubuntu, Cantarell, &#39;Helvetica Neue&#39;, &#39;Fira Sans&#39;, &#39;Droid Sans&#39;, Arial, sans-serif;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_table {
  display: table;
  border-collapse: collapse;
  margin-left: auto;
  margin-right: auto;
  color: #333333;
  font-size: 16px;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  width: auto;
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 2px;
  border-top-color: #A8A8A8;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 2px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #A8A8A8;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 2px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_heading {
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  text-align: center;
  border-bottom-color: #FFFFFF;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 1px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 1px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_title {
  color: #333333;
  font-size: 125%;
  font-weight: initial;
  padding-top: 4px;
  padding-bottom: 4px;
  border-bottom-color: #FFFFFF;
  border-bottom-width: 0;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_subtitle {
  color: #333333;
  font-size: 85%;
  font-weight: initial;
  padding-top: 0;
  padding-bottom: 4px;
  border-top-color: #FFFFFF;
  border-top-width: 0;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_bottom_border {
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_col_headings {
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 2px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 1px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 1px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_col_heading {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  font-size: 100%;
  font-weight: normal;
  text-transform: inherit;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 1px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 1px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
  vertical-align: bottom;
  padding-top: 5px;
  padding-bottom: 6px;
  padding-left: 5px;
  padding-right: 5px;
  overflow-x: hidden;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_column_spanner_outer {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  font-size: 100%;
  font-weight: normal;
  text-transform: inherit;
  padding-top: 0;
  padding-bottom: 0;
  padding-left: 4px;
  padding-right: 4px;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_column_spanner_outer:first-child {
  padding-left: 0;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_column_spanner_outer:last-child {
  padding-right: 0;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_column_spanner {
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
  vertical-align: bottom;
  padding-top: 5px;
  padding-bottom: 6px;
  overflow-x: hidden;
  display: inline-block;
  width: 100%;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_group_heading {
  padding: 8px;
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  font-size: 100%;
  font-weight: initial;
  text-transform: inherit;
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 2px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 1px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 1px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
  vertical-align: middle;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_empty_group_heading {
  padding: 0.5px;
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  font-size: 100%;
  font-weight: initial;
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 2px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
  vertical-align: middle;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_striped {
  background-color: rgba(128, 128, 128, 0.05);
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_from_md &gt; :first-child {
  margin-top: 0;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_from_md &gt; :last-child {
  margin-bottom: 0;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_row {
  padding-top: 8px;
  padding-bottom: 8px;
  padding-left: 5px;
  padding-right: 5px;
  margin: 10px;
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 1px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 1px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 1px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
  vertical-align: middle;
  overflow-x: hidden;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_stub {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  font-size: 100%;
  font-weight: initial;
  text-transform: inherit;
  border-right-style: solid;
  border-right-width: 2px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
  padding-left: 12px;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_summary_row {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  text-transform: inherit;
  padding-top: 8px;
  padding-bottom: 8px;
  padding-left: 5px;
  padding-right: 5px;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_first_summary_row {
  padding-top: 8px;
  padding-bottom: 8px;
  padding-left: 5px;
  padding-right: 5px;
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 2px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_grand_summary_row {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  text-transform: inherit;
  padding-top: 8px;
  padding-bottom: 8px;
  padding-left: 5px;
  padding-right: 5px;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_first_grand_summary_row {
  padding-top: 8px;
  padding-bottom: 8px;
  padding-left: 5px;
  padding-right: 5px;
  border-top-style: double;
  border-top-width: 6px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_table_body {
  border-top-style: solid;
  border-top-width: 2px;
  border-top-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-bottom-style: solid;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_footnotes {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  border-bottom-style: none;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 2px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 2px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_footnote {
  margin: 0px;
  font-size: 90%;
  padding: 4px;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_sourcenotes {
  color: #333333;
  background-color: #FFFFFF;
  border-bottom-style: none;
  border-bottom-width: 2px;
  border-bottom-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-left-style: none;
  border-left-width: 2px;
  border-left-color: #D3D3D3;
  border-right-style: none;
  border-right-width: 2px;
  border-right-color: #D3D3D3;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_sourcenote {
  font-size: 90%;
  padding: 4px;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_left {
  text-align: left;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_center {
  text-align: center;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_right {
  text-align: right;
  font-variant-numeric: tabular-nums;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_font_normal {
  font-weight: normal;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_font_bold {
  font-weight: bold;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_font_italic {
  font-style: italic;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_super {
  font-size: 65%;
}

#ydhgsekrci .gt_footnote_marks {
  font-style: italic;
  font-size: 65%;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;ydhgsekrci&#34; style=&#34;overflow-x:auto;overflow-y:auto;width:auto;height:auto;&#34;&gt;&lt;table class=&#34;gt_table&#34;&gt;
  &lt;thead class=&#34;gt_header&#34;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th colspan=&#34;1&#34; class=&#34;gt_heading gt_title gt_font_normal&#34; style&gt;Cool table&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th colspan=&#34;1&#34; class=&#34;gt_heading gt_subtitle gt_font_normal gt_bottom_border&#34; style&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;thead class=&#34;gt_col_headings&#34;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th class=&#34;gt_col_heading gt_columns_bottom_border gt_center&#34; rowspan=&#34;1&#34; colspan=&#34;1&#34;&gt;X1&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody class=&#34;gt_table_body&#34;&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td class=&#34;gt_row gt_center&#34;&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td class=&#34;gt_row gt_center&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
  
  
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Options&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also initialize a setup chunk with global chunk options like below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;knitr::opts_chunk$set(include = TRUE, warning = FALSE) # Random chunk options&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/rmarkdown-cheatsheet.pdf&#34;&gt;cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;knitting-to-different-file-formats&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.5 Knitting to Different File Formats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Cmd or Ctrl + Shift + K&lt;/code&gt; to knit to chosen format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Knit button in the RStudio toolbar to knit to some other format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alternately, edit the YAML header at the top of the file. Options include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;output:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  pdf_document: default

  word_document: default

  html_document: default&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;more-resources-1&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.6 More Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Xie, Yihue. &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/rmarkdown/yihui-xie.html&#34;&gt;R Markdown: The Definite Guide&lt;/a&gt; (written in &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/bookdown/&#34;&gt;Bookdown&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R for Data Science (R4DS) &lt;a href=&#34;https://r4ds.had.co.nz/r-markdown.html&#34;&gt;Chapter&lt;/a&gt; on Rmds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Police Stop Bunching: A Curious Case of Rounding Off</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/police-stop-bunching-a-curious-case-of-rounding-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/police-stop-bunching-a-curious-case-of-rounding-off/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/b-hemanth/policing_analysis&#34;&gt;Code and ReadMe&lt;/a&gt;: something curious I found while playing with policing data a la the Stanford Open Policing Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is happening here, officer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://b-hemanth.com/post/2020-07-13-police-stop-bunching-a-curious-case-of-rounding-off_files/stops.png&#34; alt=&#34;You&amp;rsquo;ve heard of rounding away criminals, but what about rounding off?&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harvard Course Enrollment: Big Winners and Losers</title>
      <link>https://b-hemanth.com/post/harvard-course-enrollment-big-winners-and-losers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://b-hemanth.com/post/harvard-course-enrollment-big-winners-and-losers/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/b-hemanth/harvard_courses_enrolment_analysis&#34;&gt;Code and ReadMe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;biggest-departmental-changes-in-enrolments-at-harvard&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biggest Departmental Changes in Enrolments at Harvard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://b-hemanth.com/post/course_enrol.png&#34; alt=&#34;courses&#34; width=&#34;800&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;biggest-drops-in-enrolment&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biggest Drops in Enrolment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://b-hemanth.com/post/courses 1.png&#34; alt=&#34;courses&#34; width=&#34;700&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;biggest-new-classes&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biggest New Classes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://b-hemanth.com/post/c2.png&#34; alt=&#34;courses&#34; width=&#34;700&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
